Richard Murray Research Material Regarding Abbott Handerson Thayer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Richard Murray research material regarding Abbott Handerson Thayer
1948-2004, bulk 1994-2001
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Murray, Richard
9.0 linear feet
The Richard Murray research material regarding Abbot Handerson Thayer measures 9.0 linear feet and dates from 1948 to 2004, with the bulk of the material dating from 1994 to 2001. Project files primarily document Murray's work on the 1999 exhibition "Abbott Thayer: The Nature of Art" and subsequent Thayer book project. Also found are extensive research files on Abbott Handerson Thayer and his specific works of art as well as photographic materials depicting Thayer, his family, studio, house, and works of art.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 2011 by the Smithsonian American Art Museum via George Gurney, curator.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds several collections related to Abbott Handerson Thayer. These include the Abbott Handerson Thayer and Thayer family papers, 1851-1999; research material on Abbott Handerson Thayer and other artists, 1895-1990, donated by Thomas B. Brumbaugh; the Abbott Handerson Thayer letter and drawings to Caroline Peddle Ball, circa 1890-1893; "The Drawings of Abbott Thayer", by Elizabeth Robins Pennell, circa 1921; and the Nelson and Henry C. White research material, 1898-1978, which includes many letters, photographs, and other material originally belonging to the Thayer family.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Richard Murray (1942-2006) was a curator and art historian at the Smithsonian American Art Museum in Washington, D.C. Murray specialized in the works of Abbott Thayer and curated the 1999 exhibition, "Abbott Thayer: The Nature of Art." Before his death Murray was researching to write a book on Thayer's paintings and his involvement with conservation projects.
Scope and Content Note
The Richard Murray research material regarding Abbot Handerson Thayer measures 9.0 linear feet and dates from 1948 to 2004, with the bulk of the material dating from 1994 to 2001. Project files primarily document Murray's work on the 1999 exhibition "Abbott Thayer: The Nature of Art" and subsequent Thayer book project. Also found are extensive research files on Abbott Handerson Thayer and his specific works of art as well as photographic materials depicting Thayer, his family, studio, house, and works of art.
Project files document Richard Murray's research projects regarding Abbott Handerson Thayer. Found here is Murray's correspondence with fellow Thayer scholars, collectors, art museums, and Thayer family members. Also included are planning documents, loan forms, press clippings, conservation requests, checklists and other materials for the exhibition "Abbott Thayer: The Nature of Art" which Murray curated at the Smithsonian American Art Museum (formerly National Museum of American Art) in 1999. Additional project files are primarily for his proposed book on Abbott Thayer and include research grant applications, fundraising, photograph orders, and reviews of the initial manuscript.
Research files contain documentation on archival collections regarding Thayer, subject files on family members, models, and friends of Thayer, private and museum collections of his artwork, and other subject's relevant to Thayer's career as an artist. Files may include Murray's correspondence and notes. However, the bulk of the material consists of photocopies or microfilm print-outs of archival documents, newspaper clippings, and other printed material. Also found are files on specific works of art by Thayer. These files may contain catalog descriptions, provenance information, correspondence, and images of the work of art.
Photographs depict Thayer, his family, friends, studio, house, and his artwork. Also found are negatives, color transparencies, and slides of these photographs. Of note are photographs of x-rays of Thayer paintings. Researchers should note that all photographs of Thayer, his family, house, studio, and artwork are copy prints of original photographs which Richard Murray requested from the owners for his research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 3 series:
Series 1: Project Files, 1990-2004 (Box 1-2; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Research Files, 1948-2004 (Box 2-8; 6.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Photographic Materials, 1961, circa 1990s-2001 (Box 8-9; 1.7 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Thayer, Abbott Handerson, 1849-1921; Smithsonian American Art Museum
Subjects-Topical:
Painters--New Hampshire--Dublin; Artists' studios-Photographs
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Slides (photographs)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Project Files,1990-2004, Series 1:; (Box 1-2; 1.2 linear feet)
  Project files document Richard Murray's various research projects regarding Abbott Handerson Thayer. Included are records regarding the exhibition "Abbott Thayer: The Nature of Art" which he curated at the Smithsonian American Art Museum (formerly National Museum of American Art) in 1999. These files include planning documents, loan forms, press clippings, conservation requests, exhibition text, and exhibition checklists. Additional project files are primarily for his proposed book on Abbott Thayer and include research grant applications, fundraising, photograph orders, and reviews of the initial manuscript. Also found is Murray's correspondence regarding his Thayer projects. Correspondence is with fellow Thayer scholars, collectors, art museums, and Thayer family members.
  - Collections-Based Research Grant, 1999-2000, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Contacts, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence regarding Thayer Projects, 1990-2004, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
  - Desk Calendars, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Impressionism Installation Draft Checklist, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Monadnock Seminar, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Museum of American Art Graph Exhibition Schedule, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Outline for Abbott Thayer Book, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photograph Orders, 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photograph Orders, Frick Art Reference Library, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Reviews of Manuscript, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Thayer Book Possible Sponsors, circa 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition, "Abbott Thayer: The Nature of Art" (Box 1)
    - Bibliography, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Book Text, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Brochure, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Budget and Expenditures, 1996-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Conservation Requests and Reports, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Exhibition Approval, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Exhibition Planning Documents, 1994-1999, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Images Dropped from Book, 1997, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Loans, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Opening Reception, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Permissions to X-Ray, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Press Clippings, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Special Exhibition Fund Grant Application, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Special Exhibition Fund Grant Narrative, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Wall Text, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Working Exhibition Checklists, circa 1996-1999, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-39)
    - Working Exhibition Checklists, circa 1996-1999, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Research Files, 1948-2004, Series 2:; (Box 2-8; 6.1 linear feet)
  Research files contain documentation on archival collections regarding Thayer, subject files on family members, models, and friends of Thayer, private and museum collections of his artwork, and other subject's relevant to Thayer's career as an artist. Of note is a group of research files on concealing coloration, and files on the "Centennial Exhibition of Paintings by Abbott Handerson Thayer." Files may include Murray's correspondence and notes. However, the bulk of the material consists of photocopies or microfilm print-outs of archival documents, newspaper clippings, and other printed material.
  Murray also maintained a set of research files on specific works of art by Thayer. Folder headings for these files he included the title of the work and in most cases the gallery, museum, or private owner of the work. Some files do not include owner information. The files may contain catalog descriptions, provenance information, correspondence, and images of the work of art.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically. There is also a grouping of unsorted research material which may relate to or duplicate material in other files. General research files are followed by a separate arrangement of files on specific works of art which are arranged alphabetically by title. In most cases folder headings have been transcribed from Murray's original folder labels.
  - Abbott Handerson Thayer Papers, Sketches, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Abbott Handerson Thayer Papers, Sketchbooks, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Abbott Thayer Death Mask/Life Mask, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Addison Gallery of American Art, 1997, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Audubon Society, circa 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Background on Abbott Thayer, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bartlett Family Collection, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bloede Family, circa 1996-2004, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Bolle Collection, circa 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Braun Collection, circa 1997 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Brooklyn Art Association, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Brooklyn Museum, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Carnegie Institute Records, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Castano Gallery Records, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Centennial Exhibition of Paintings by Abbott Handerson Thayer, 1949-1951, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Charles Lang Freer Papers, circa 1990s, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
  - Chesterwood Collection, 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Chronologies, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Clemens, Samuel (Mark Twain), circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Concealing Coloration (Box 2)
    - Excerpts from Book Concealing-Coloration in the Animal Kingdom, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Exhibitions, circa 1990s, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Franklin Roosevelt, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - General, circa 1990s, 2000, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-34)
    - Icebergs, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Military Camo (Other than Roosevelt), circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Ship Camouflage, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Theodore Roosevelt, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Corot, J. B. C., circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Decorative Angels, circa 1997 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Documentation regarding Photographs of Abbott Thayer and Thayer Family, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dow, Thomas Millie, circa 1990s-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dublin, New Hampshire, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Loan List, "Abbott H. Thayer Retrospective" at Everson Museum of Art, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Records, circa 1990s, 2000, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Fashion (Hats and Birds), 2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Faulkner, Barry, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fisher, Ellen Thayer, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Freer Gallery of Art Collection, 1997-2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Frames, circa 1990s, 2000, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Fuller, Elizabeth, circa 1999 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Gellatly, John, circa 1990s, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - General Theories, Statements, Opinions on Art, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gerome, Jean Leon, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Gladys Thayer Reasoner on Abbott Thayer's Death, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Helena DeKay Gilder Diary, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Henry Allison Photographs and Related Correspondence, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Inventory of American Paintings, Artist Index, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - James, William, 1990s-2000 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Journal and Magazine Articles, Book Excerpts, circa 1990s, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 26-29)
  - Juley Photograph Collection, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Kent, Rockwell, circa 1999 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - La Farge, John, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Letters, Abbott Thayer and Thayer Family, circa 1990s, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 33-35)
  - Letters, Abbott Thayer to Clara May, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Letters from Artists to Abbott Thayer, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Location Lists for Thayer Paintings, circa 1997 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Macbeth Gallery Records, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - McIlhenny, Charles Morgan, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Meryman Collection, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Meryman, Richard, circa 2000 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Milch Gallery Records, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Missing Memorial Exhibition Paintings, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Morse, Henry Dutton, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mystery of "Gladys" Painting, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Museum of American Art, List of Works by Thayer, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Nelson White Collection, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Nelson White Papers, Letters, circa 1990s, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Nelson White Papers, Mrs. Thayer's Scrapbook, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Nelson White Papers, Reminiscences of Gladys Thayer, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Nelson White Papers, Thayer Writings, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - New Hampshire State House, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Articles, circa 1990s, (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 11-16)
  - Notes from Susan Hobbs's Trip to New Hampshire, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Obituaries and Tributes, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Other Angels, circa 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Paris, circa 1990s, 2000, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Perception, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Plunket Collection, circa 1998-1999, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 23-25)
  - Property Documents and Thayer Estate, 1976, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Pumpelly, Raphael, circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Quotes by and about Abbott Thayer, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Renaissance Typologies, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Research Paper, Elizabeth Lee, "Painting Against the Modern: Beauty, Filth and Disease in the Art of Abbott Thayer", circa 1997 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Research Paper, Karen Phillips, "Abbott Handerson Thayer and the Development of His Winged Figures", 1986 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Research Paper, Elizabeth Walmsley, "A Preliminary Investigation into the Painting Techniques of Abbott Handerson Thayer", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Research Trip, London and Glasgow, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Research Trip, Mid-West, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Research Trips, New England, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Research Trip, New Hampshire, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Research Trip, New York City, circa 1992 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Self-Portraits, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Society of American Artists, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Stevenson, Robert Louis (Stevenson Memorial), circa 1997-1999, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
  - Stevenson, Robert Louis (Stevenson Memorial), circa 1997-1999, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Stillman Collection, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - St. Ives, Cornwall, circa 1990-1996 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Student Records, circa 2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Summer Teaching, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Taber, Edward Martin, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Teaching, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Thesis, Virginia Lee Pledger, "Abbott H. Thayer's Mural Florence Protecting the Arts", 1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Thayer, Emma, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Thayer, Gerald, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Thayer, Gladys, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Thayer's Models, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Thayer on Restoration, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Thayer on Women, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Thayer Reviews, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Thayer Students, 1948-1950, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - Thayer, William H., circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Thomas Brumbaugh Papers, circa 1990s, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 21-23)
  - Vose Gallery Records, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Weir, Julian Alden, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - White, Stanford, circa 1990s-2000 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Whittaker, John Bernard, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Research Material, Miscellaneous Unsorted, circa 1990s, (10 folders) (Box 5, Folder 29-38)
  - Research To Do, circa 1996-2000 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Research Not Using, circa 1990s, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - To Be Filed, circa 2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Research on Specific Works of Art (Box 6)
    - General Research on Works of Art by Thayer, circa 1997-2000, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Questionable Works, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Alma Wollerman, Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - An Angel, Milwaukee Art Museum, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Angel, National Museum of American Art, circa 1990s (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - The Angel, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1994-1998 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Angel of Dawn, St. Anselm's Abbey School, circa 1996-1998 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Anne Mumford Palmer, Memorial Art Gallery, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Azores, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Below Mount Monadnock, Hood Museum of Art, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Berkshire Wood, Curtis Cheney, 1997-2000 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Blue Jays in Winter, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Blue Ribbon, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Boy and Angel, Albright-Knox Art Gallery, 1997-2000 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - A Bride, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Brother and Sister, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Capri, Freer Gallery of Art, circa 1994-1997 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Caritas, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, circa 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Cattle, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Cattle by a Stream, 1995, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Child With Kittens, 1997-1999 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Clearing, Washington County Museum of Fine Arts, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Concord River from French's Landing, Chesterwood, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Copperhead Snake on Dead Leaves, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Cornish Headlands, Freer Gallery of Art, circa 1992-1997 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Cornish Headlands, National Museum of American Art, circa 1999 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - The Cotton-Tail Rabbit Among Dry Grasses and Leaves, Brooklyn Museum, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Diana, Freer Gallery of Art, circa 1995-1997 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - The Donkey, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Drawing, Neuberger Museum of Art, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Dublin Pond, New Hampshire, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Fall Landscape, Weschler's, 1972, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Flower Studies, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Forest Interior, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Frog, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Girl Arranging Her Hair, Canajoharie Library and Art Gallery, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Girl Arranging Her Hair, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Girl in Fur Hood, Brooklyn Museum, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Girl in White, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Girl in White, St. Bonaventure University, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Girl Reading, Hirshhorn Museum (Deaccessioned), circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Gladys, Memphis Brooks Museum of Art, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Half-Draped Figure, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Head, Freer Gallery of Art, circa 1992-1997 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Head of a Dog, Worcester Art Museum, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Head of a Girl, Brooklyn Museum, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Head of a Young Woman, Corcoran Gallery of Art, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Hebe, Cleveland Museum of Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Helen Sears, Toledo Museum of Art, 1992, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Heterocampa biundata (Walker), National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Hooded Warblers, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Jessie Jay Burge, Brooklyn Museum, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Josephine Balestier, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Landscape, University of Maine, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Landscape at Fountainbleu, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Light of the Smudge and the After Sunset Glow, Harvard University, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Little Girl With Flowers, Montgomery Gallery, Pomona College, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Lunar Caterpillar, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Maids in the Meadow, Colby College Museum of Art, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Male Ruffled Grouse in the Forest, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Male Wood Duck, National Museum of American Art, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Male Wood Duck in a Forest Pool, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Margaret MacKittrick, Indianapolis Museum of Art, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Meditation, Butler Institute, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Minerva in a Chariot, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Monadnock, Jean Plunket, 1997-1999 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Monadnock Angel, Addison Gallery, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Monadnock in Winter, Freer Gallery of Art, 1995-1999 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Monadnock Mountain, Freer Gallery of Art, circa 1992-1997 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Monadnock No. 2, Freer Gallery of Art, circa 1995-1997 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Mother and Child, RISD Museum, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Mount Monadnock (1897), 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Mount Monadnock, Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Mount Monadnock, Joan and Byron Lapham, 1997-2000 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Mount Monadnock, Paul Kossey, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Mount Monadnock, University of New Hampshire, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Mrs. William F. Milton, Metropolitan Museum of Art, circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - My Children, Brooklyn Museum, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - My Children, National Museum of American Art, circa 1992-1997 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - My Daughter Mary, Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Mystic, Connecticut, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Noon, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - The Old Sailmaker, Chesterwood, circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Peacock in the Woods, National Museum of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Pensive Model, circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Portrait of Alexina Mease White, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Portrait of Alice Rich, circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Portrait of the Artist's Eldest Daughter, Freer Gallery of Art, 1995-1999 (Box 7, Folder 29)